So this is interesting because we can have
a nice theorem which says that, so this particular
form of UCB is actually called UCB 1 right,
and in the literature if you generally see
you see be without any qualifier Center to
it usually means UCB1 okay, there are many
variants on it we are not going to look at
all the variants that is like normal UCB then
you see be revisited you see be improved UCB2
right so, there are many many variations of
you see be right and each one gives you a
slightly better critical results than the
one that I am going to write down right, and
sometimes involving exponentially harder analysis.
.
UCB1 is fairly trivial compared to the other
algorithm set that were proposed later and
just want to give you a flavor of the kind
of work that is done in this area right, so
I am NOT going to get into the other things
but we will certainly put all those papers
up on Moodle, if people want to read they
can read those. Another thing about UCB1 is
that we can have arbitrary reward distributions
so, some of the other algorithms that are
out there assume say Bernoulli rewards and
if for showing their results and so on so
forth the right thing about UCB 1 is arbitrary
well.
.
So capital ?I is Q *A* - Q* essentially this
means the loss that you will incur if ,you
play I is expected loss that will incur if
you play I instead of playing A*, remember
what A* is the max over A of Q * a right so,
that is a star max A of Q *A is a A* right
s, they will always denote by a start the
optimal action right so, what this is tell
you so the regret right this upper bounded
by eight times ln n by ?I the summation running
over all the non optimal arms ,why all the
non optimal ops? Because ?I is 0 for optimal
arm, so I do not really want that to figure
in the summation okay, plus 1+ ?2/3 that is
a magic constant okay, times summation over
all j ?j right.
And here i am being little sloppy i have to
exclude the optimal arm here also but i do
not because it is 0 anyway, ?j 0 anyway so,
I mean symmetrically just as I have the summation
ER I should have the summation there, but
I can be a little sloppy and I can write it
like that because, i do not have worried about
the additional 0 terms I’m adding it okay,
great. How did we get from here to there or
more importantly how do we get this expression?
I so, before we go on so I want to introduce
a little bit of notation here
that is a term that tells you the number of
times it is a random variable that represents
the number of times I have played arm I in
the first n trials okay.
Number of times I have played out my in the
first ten trials that makes sense, so then
i can write me regret after n trails as summation
over i expected value of that times ?i, people
get that so they expected the regret that
I expect to have after n time steps is I will
take each action, look at the number of times
I, would have played that action till that
time right, multiply it by the regret of playing
that action right. So if i play the optimal
action then the regulator is 0,so if i play
some sub optimal action then i will be adding
that ?i times the number of times i have played
that sub optimal action I right.
So this is essentially my definition of regret
so i have a nova formal way of writing down
my definition of regret, this is clear any
questions? Okay. so one more notation is one
thing which I yeah so one more notation i
will have here, it is a random variable that
denotes the reward that i obtained for playing
action I at time n, some n ok some arbitrary
n time n if I play action I write what I see
the word that I get right? since we are assuming
everything is stationary right so the expectation
of this will be, this will tell me people
are following it or not, so what is Xin the
reward I get for playing are my a time n right
what is the expected value of that somebody
say something.
One of you put your hand up and say something,
so that i can very hard for me to make out
in that murmur and hand, Q*I, people see why
since we are assuming things are stationary
this expectation is really not going to depend
on n, so then it becomes expected reward I
get for pulling our my which is essentially
Q*I okay, great. So anything else that I need
to do notation wise so, essentially to show
this result right, what I am going to try
and show is that, this guy is bounded and
I am going to show that that k is bounded
so what I am going to show? We're going to
show that the expected value of Tj(n)or Ti(n)
is bounded by 8/ ?i2 ln n so, since i multiply
by another delta here to get the regret so
that will get me the first term in the regret
and some constant here which will get me the
second term the regret. Expectations of the
number of times plane and multiplying it by
some value ?i which is calculated at the end
stage right, it's not calculated at the nth
stage it's calculated by using their true
values that's Q* you do not know the values
but it's just a definition is a quantity that's
the expected regret that you are going to
get for playing arm I, this is the expected
loss you would accrue for playing arm I.
If I had played the best arm over and over
again right, if I played the best term over
and over again I would get Q*A* if you play
arm I am going to get Q*A right, so the loss
i am going to get this Q*A*- Q*A right, so
this is what I am denoting by ?i this is the
loss that they expect a crew for playing arm
I, let us think that one norm right and if
we keep playing the arm repeatedly the total
loss i am going to accrue is ?i a times the
number of times i will pay i write n dice
on this overall the arms. So one of these
arms in the summation or one or more of these
arms and we do not know one or more of these
arms in the summation would be optimal.
And for those terms delta i will be 0, so
the regret require the contribution to the
regret will be 0 and all the other sub optimal
arms will contribute ?i to the regret. Because
I am assuming the reward distributions are
stationary, I do remember I said you are deciding
the by tossing a coin but you do not change
the coin right because you do not change the
coin does not matter when they toss the coin
the probability of it coming up heads will
be the same whether it toss it the first time
or they toss it at the tenth time I pull they
are the probability of it coming heads will
be the same and that is the expectation, right
so the expectation will be the same right.
so one way to think about the X this expectation
is right so, I do multiple experiments and
I do several experiments every time starting
from time 0 right, I do i do like the millions
of experiments every time I start from time
0 and I keep pulling arms for some number
of time steps and then i reset my whole system
start from time 0 and pull for another say
100 time steps or something like that right
when i do this experiments like this in the
10th time step if I pull on three right so
in this million experiments some number of
times I would have pulled on three in the
10thtime step okay, then I'll take all the
rewards I saw then I'll take the average of
that right that is one way of thinking about
what this expectation means.
So now you understand it does not matter whether
I pulled on three at 10th step or whether
a pull on three at the thousandth time step
if i take this expectation across these million
trails, it will be the same. So that is essentially
what we're saying here okay, is it is it clear
so what we are trying to show is this right
so if you are able to show this then we are
all done as long as this constant here evaluates
to 1+?2/3 here proof is all done okay. Now
we have to now go and start counting that
okay, so here things start get getting interesting
so you want to complete the proof so, before
I move on with the proof i will need one more
i need one more fact, so
they're on this whole set of results in probability
theory called concentration inequalities or
concentration bounds.
They are sometimes called large deviation
bounds okay, these are essentially results
that relate the true expectations of distributions
okay, with estimated values of those expectations
from samples not this expectations in different
kinds of statistics you have different bounds
you have bounced on expectations you have
bounds on variance right and so on so forth,
right so essentially the idea behind these
bounds is to kind of characterize right so,
given a certain number of samples from which
you are estimating a statistic and the statistics
in this case will for the one that we are
interested in is the expectation right.
So we are interested in the expectation as
a statistic right, so I have some number of
samples from which I makes estimating this
expectation right and i have the true expectations
right so as the number of samples increases
how quickly or how slowly does this estimation
approach my true expectation so there is something
that we want to characterize so we will talk
about one such bond which is a very popular
plant which applied all over the place okay,
so if you are going to do anything in machine
learning forget about RL anything that has
remotely shades of theoretical results in
machine learning it's a good idea to know
more about concentration bones but at least
the least you should know as a bad thing sure
enough bonds or sheriff of bonds.
.
So this is a very specialized form of the
bound I am writing at very narrow form of
the bond i am writing specifically for this
setting that we are interested in right the
Shernoff bond is slightly more general than
what i am stating now right so, you can look
it up I mean so you can look up I don’t
know your favorite online resource at Wikipedia
or what a mathematical one of those things
right so it will give you a more expanded
bound. So you can see the setup here I am
assuming that x1 to xn are random variables
right each one with a range 0 to 1, that is
kind of putting it here and if it is not in
the range 0 to 1 you will have to do some
kind of normalization in the bound right,
but for the time being let's assume it's in
the range 0 to 1.
And such that the expected value of XT right
given all the variables that came before that
is µ and then this holds for all T basically
it, essentially means that all of the variables
have a mean µ, all the variables each one
independently x1 is a random variable with
mean µ and the range 0 to 1 X 2 is a random
variable with mean µ in the range 0 to 1
okay. So essentially that is what we are assuming
and I am defining another random variable
which we call SN which is essentially summing
up all the X 1 to Xl and divide by n, okay
so get that.
So what I am I trying to estimate us with
SL you right and try to estimate them is µ
so, one right now let us try to make this
little concrete in our case so, that it becomes
easier for you to understand right so x1 to
xn or random variables that are corresponding
to different times, I have pulled the same
arm I right so I have pulled arm I n times
right, so every time I pull the arm I am going
to get some reward from the range 0 to 1 right,
since I am assuming it is a stationary distribution
all these rewards will have the same mean
µ ,correct? And SL is the average right this
SN is essentially make you j and if you think
about it so, QJ is like one sample of my random
variable SN, is it what I mean by saying QJ
is a sample of SL because, they said is a
random variable right what is QJ it is one
realization of that random variable, because
I have taken actual samples and taken the
average it is one realization of that random
variable right.
And what I am going to now tell you is okay
given that i have taken n samples so, in our
case it will be NJ samples right given that
i have taken NJ samples, how can you relate
QJ with what how can I relate QJ with Q *J
okay, so given that I have taken NJ samples
which is my n here how can relate QJ with
Q *J okay. So this is how the hafting bound
is applicable in our case right so i will
write down the expression i am not going to
prove it okay, so that will get little bit
more involved write down the expression and
after that we can apply it in there deriving
those bonds okay.
.
So essentially what i have here is now the
probability that SN greater than or equal
to µ plus some e, where it will do a here
but because a is action right sudden want
to confuse A for action with something else
yeah, this is what this is a problem with
translating on the fly okay, fine so it should
be n or n2? o what does this mean the probability
that my SN will be far away from my µ in
one direction so µ+e is some use a true mean,
SN is estimated mean the probability that
SN will be greater than at least e from µ
right is lesser than e-2e2 right, so the smaller
the e , what happen? Smaller the probability
or larger the probability larger the probability
smaller the epsilon larger the probability
right so larger the probability of me making
an error, I mean if I want to be really really
confident then I need more and more samples
right.
If I want e to be very small then n has to
be very large only then I will get a high
probability format right what about this it
says in the other direction probability that
the estimate I make will be far away from
e, basically below e right is again bounded
by the same expression.